Guide to the Charlie Cobb Interviews, 2012-2013 RL.11333
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- This Nonviolent Stuff Will Get You Killed Interviews, 2012-2013; 3
  - Donaldson, Ivanhoe, 2013-04-23; 37
    - Ivanhoe Donaldson1 april 23 2013.mp3, 0:35:32 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. In person at Brown University in Providence, Rhode Island. Discussed when Donaldson first hear the name SNCC and thoughts. Discussed SNCC beginnings, was apart of October meeting that SNCC began formalizing SNCC. Issue in SNCC regarding direct action vs nonviolence, In MS nonviolence, ex: sit ins were direct action. Discussing how he got his start into SNCC in Louisville. Donaldson didn't think of nonviolence in a philosophical way, religious people in SNCC were philosophical committed to Nonviolence, others weren't but worked together. Donaldson wasn't with the gun people or the philosophically nonviolent people. "Can't beat a tank with a Molotov cocktail", impressed by people who can be pacifists, requires lots of inner strength. Discussed grassroots organizing and discussion of nonviolence with the local people.
    - Ivanhoe on nonviolence August 15 2013.mp3, 1:20:45 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. Telephone interview. Nonviolence is the way to survive the future. Human beings are violent, either by running, hiding or participating in it. Violence has never changed anything, it makes realignments of power and authority. Culture we grow up in says you step to me, I'll step to you. Culture of the human race. Incarceration of people, majority in prison for drugs. No voices were there to speak about nonviolence after the movement. Post Civil Rights era: discussion of non violence never center of the discussion was used as a means for the movement. There's no values training, The philosophically committed to nonviolence still exist but they don't organize in the communities. The Rev Lawson type of people have always existed, their tools became relevant because of the mission of civil rights, the mission got consumed by reform politics, e.i: voting rights, immigration, etc. When the generation fulfilled it's limited mission, it ended. A nonviolent movement against violence (Of all sorts/across the board), you have to have a conversation about violence itself, sort of like groups like the quakers, Jim Lawson (Bernard lafayatte who was a student of Lawson), Thoreau. No one wants to hear about violence as a concept, we deal with it more as an issue for example, "domestic violence", get boys to stop being on girls. Deacons for Defense and groups like that protected nonviolent people, nonviolence made the change not the guns. Guns never allowed for discussion. People romanticize guerilla warfare. Discussion of Stokely Carmichael's call out about Black Power= how did it get interpreted as violent: white guilt and white arrogance. Marion Berry: uppity negro, white people resented him. Violence or the threat of violence being used to enforce boycott, The demands on MLK were just too phenomenal.
    - Transcript_DonaldsonIvanhoeonNonviolence_CobbTNVSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
    - Transcript_DonaldsonIvanhoePt1_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Dorsey, LC, undated; 38
    - LC at Fannie Lou Hamer Institute.mp3, 1:11:57 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      LC at Fannie Lou Hamer Institute (poor quality). A recording of a lecture. Discussing experiences during the movement, confronting the KKK who were outside her house and they left, comparing the community today compared to the past, Conditions in the south for Black people during the movement time. (The last half of the interview is a Q & A session)
  - Evers, Myrlie, 2012-07-26; 39
    - Myrlie Evers at Alcorn July 26 2012.mp3, 1:11:16 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Discusses Medgar's life/attitude before/after serving in the military, Charles and Medgar's thoughts about the Mau Mau movement in Kenya & forming one in the US, The changing of the name of their child on the birth certificate, meeting Medgar for the first time, anecdotal and biographical information about Medgar Evers.
  - Harding, Vincent, 2013-07-19; 40
    - vincent harding1July 19 2013.mp3, 0:06:03 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Part 1. Telephone interview. Very short interview. Harding is giving edits to Charlie's book.
    - vincent harding2 July 19 2013.mp3, 1:04:17 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Part 2. Telephone interview. More edits/comments/suggestions on Charlie's Book draft. Discussing SCLC and who might be able to discuss SCLC best.
  - Harris, Don, 2012-09-14; 41
    - Don Harris September 14 2012.mp3, 0:56:24 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Thoughts when first hearing about SNCC: Didn't know anything about what they were about. Thoughts on non violence: He was not thinking about non violence, it wasn't a factor in his interest in SNCC, he supported students being involved in the movement. Sherrod: nonviolence as a tactic, Thoughts on guns and local people protecting them with the guns. Guns presence in rural south minimized violence. No intense SNCC conversations/arguments about guns.
  - Harris, Jessie, 2012-07-24; 42
    - Jessie Harris July 24 2012.mp3, 0:52:07 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person/background noise. Discussed how people resisted the violent actions of white supremacy, experiences in the movement in SW Mississippi, Security group w/ CC Bryant, Guns, Citizenship classes/Freedom schools, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, nonviolent workshops.
    - Jessie Harris2 July 24 2012.mp3, 0:09:37 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Part 2. In person/background noise. Very short interview. Discussed support of local community of the movement, armed protection, playing golf tournaments, brief insight into school background and Atlanta SNCC conference.
  - Hartford, Bruce, 2013-07-26; 43
    - Bruce Hartford July 26 2012.mp3, 0:57:36 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. SCLC in Tuscaloosa,al was protected by group of Korean war veterans. He was on the field staff, very hieratical organization, SCLC staff meetings where about getting the work done, tactics not really philosophy, strategics, non violence and violence like SNCC. Debate between philosophical non violent (minority) and tactical nonviolent (majority), (I'd rather but caught with it than without it) non violent was a given on protests, debate came with local people and armed guards at night and carrying guns outside the demonstrations. Experiences in Selma,Grenada,Crenshaw County,AL. Also worked with CORE, SCOPE, he had workshops with young people.
  - Jones, Charles, 2013-06-07; 44
    - Charles Jones June 7 2013 Part1.mp3, 1:18:23 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. Telephone interview. biographical, discussed his movement beginnings divinity student at Johnson C Smith University, attended festival in Vienna, Austria and was asked to sit before the House committee on Un American activities, joined Woolworth's sit ins in Greensboro. What nonviolence is? To Jones it is a lifestyle. Beginnings of SNCC, He may have been the one to include "non violent" to add the nonviolent to student coordinating committee. Voting registration is direct action
    - Charles Jones June 8 2013 Part 2.mp3, 1:10:29 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. Telephone interview. Harry Belafonte invited McDew, Diane, Sherrod, Jenkins to come to Washington DC for a concert, talked about the next phase of the movement, this interview is largely focused on voter registration, McComb Mississippi, everyone had gotten arrested and he asked Harry Belafonte for help with money and he sent some money. Effect of SNCC presence on the community, it introduced a different type of violence. SNCC left McComb to regroup in Atlanta once they got out of jail. Results of meeting; voter registration was an essential move to empower blacks in rural south. Albany,GA bus boycott & mass meetings. First freedom singers: Charles Jones, Sherrod, cordell,Bernice and ruthie harris.
    - Transcript_JonesCharlesPt1_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
    - Transcript_JonesCharlesPt2_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - King, Lonnie, 2013-02-11; 45
    - Lonnie King February 11 2013.mp3, 0:46:36 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Has been transcribed.
    - Transcript_KingLonnie_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Ladner, Dorie, 2013-05-30; 46
    - Dorie Ladner May 30 2013.mp3, 1:16:22 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. Autobiographical interview for most part. First experience handling a gun, Deacons for justice, Charles Evers (Not a fan), discussed Medgar Evers: a role model/someone to look up to, first time in the Mississippi delta was in finding COFO there (curfew was unusual). The rest of the interview discusses experiences in the movement and people in the movement.
    - Transcript_LadnerDorie_CCobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Lafayette, Bernard, 2013-03-01; 47
    - Bernard Lafayette March 1 2013.mp3, 1:07:57 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Where did the name SNCC come from? Said Jim Lawson may have a better idea of the answer. Nashville group was unique, 3 months of training by Jim Lawson, committed to nonviolence. Theme: Nonviolence, what is it? & feelings/thoughts behind it. Believed in King-ian nonviolence: passive resistance not pacificism. Leon Sullivan boycott, gang tactics to enforce boycott in Philadelphia. One girl told him not to interfere with her suffering. Nonviolence is not passive. 3 state conspiracy to kill him, CORE and Medgar evers. Non violence sometimes unnervered attackers, practical i.e jail time or worse, un-violence between violence and non violence lodged in community. Grew up around guns.
  - Lawson, Jim, 2013-08-05; 48
    - Jim Lawson conversation August 5 2013.mp3, 0:13:58 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Short interview: Talks about the correlation between guns and southern culture, because it was a hunting culture, mostly every household had a gun. Also asks goes over how SNCC got its name, Lawson thinks he suggested the name SNCC. Speaks briefly about Nashville Group.
  - Long, Worth, 2012-03-24; 49
    - Worth Long March 24 2012.mp3, 1:31:46 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Jackson, MS. Discussed using the term unviolence and how it was applied and thoughts on nonviolence as a philosophy or as a way of life, His role in the movement (becoming a replacement for Bernard Lafayette after he was beaten and asked to go to Fisk), Watts Line, Gangs and their protection of movement people, being armed with guns plus guns and its impact on Southern culture, Little Rock community protected itself, the Bates family and using weapons to protect the house in Little Rock, deacons for defense and justice, Self Defense, Citizenship school, a little historical talk of slavery & freedom.
  - McCoy, Deborah Well, undated; 50
    - Rev Deborah Well McCoy.mp3, 0:13:57 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person in Albany, GA. Short Interview. discussed how father in general and how he was nonviolent to the core, no guns.
  - McDew, Chuck, 2012-03-23; 51
    - Chuck McDew March 23 2012.mp3, 0:28:05 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. A lot of background noise (Jackson, Mississippi): Talks about the idea that they decided not to leave local people behind when violence ensued, SNCC would not leave once things got tough. Mentions Natchez, Mississippi. Steptoe in Amite County, decided Steptoe was right and that they couldn't be there without guns. Black girls at southern university were sponsored by white men in Natchez, so It was dangerous because people weren't trustworthy. He said philosophically he never believed non violence would work, never believed in it from the beginning. He wasn't actively pursuing violence but would kill if necessary. More typical attitude in SNCC minus Jim Lawson students. More discussion on violence vs non violence and incidents of violence.
    - Chuck McDew on SNCC founding January 31 2013.mp3, 1:25:13 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. Telephone interview. "which cheek you gonna turn?" SNCC founding. How was the name SNCC proposed? Someone from the Nashville group proposed the SNCC name, believes it was Diane. Talked about SCLC meeting/conference that SNCC was created out of, how many students were ministerial students who defying powerful ministers of SCLC. After the second day of conference the Nonviolent was added to the SNCC organization name. David Forbes convinced McDew to stay. The third day SNCC was an organization that had plans for future. SNCC statement of purpose was a collective effort, did not reflect the way most SNCC members thought, not written by Jim Lawson.
    - Transcript_McDewChuck_CobbTNVSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
    - Transcript_McDewChuck_SNCC founding_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - McLaurin, Charles, 2012-03-23; 52
    - Charles McLaurin March 23 2012.mp3, 0:24:23 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. In person. Jackson, Mississippi: discussed anecdotes about Mississippi, Starts talking about the movement in the Delta, Fannie Lou Hamer really got it going. Freedom farm. Briefly discusses guns and place in the home, mostly for food.
    - Transcript_McLaurinCharles_CCobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Moses, Bob, 2013-04-25; 53
    - Bob Moses April 25 2013.mp3, 1:40:58 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. In person. Jamaica Plains, Massachusetts. Ideas about nonviolence? Non violence offense; the act of going to the courthouse is the attack itself. Conversation on the use of guns, Ella Baker was not into nonviolence, felt it was viable though. MS staff and discussion/debated/argument of guns? It didn't really happen, they knew that in McComb that there was self defense. After Stokely says black power, there was a shift. FBI reports of people commenting on non violence. Not a lot of self defense on the road
    - Transcript_MosesBob_CCobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Parker, Christopher, 2012-11-12; 54
    - Christopher Parker November12-2012.mp3, 0:24:45 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Discussing WW2 time period groups organizing specifically with black WW2 vets, black veterans on average more often resistant to white supremacy than guys who haven't served. More educated blacks more likely to be selected to serve. Desegregation of the military by Truman. White military leaders mostly southern.
  - Peacock, Willie, undated; 55
    - willie peacock with tom dent.wma, 0:31:58 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Background noise. Discussed Mississippi and Guyot
    - willie peacock with tom dent2.wma, 0:10:25 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Background noise. Short Interview. Discussed organizing within the community and making organizers out of the local people.
  - Reagon, Bernice, 2012-03-22; 56
    - Bernice Reagon march 22 2012.mp3, 0:11:46 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. In person. Jackson, Mississippi. Discussed first encounter to the name Student Nonviolent coordinating committee. The word nonviolent, what it meant, love for your fellow man=nonviolent? From Albany, GA, Grew up around guns. Took a long time to develop a concept of non-violence that worked for her. Father was active in the movement.
    - Transcript_ReagonBernice_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Robinson, Reggie, 2013-06-06; 57
    - Reggie Robinson 1 June 6 2013.mp3, 1:12:19 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Discussed Cambridge movement, Pops St.Clair (wasn't nonviolent) undertaker and his family was a prominent Black Family in Cambridge, Gloria Richardson (niece of Pop's St.Clair), Discussed how Reggie got involved with the Cambridge movement (he was working in Baltimore with CORE/SNCC) then was told he could be of assistance in Cambridge,MD, Herb St.Clair made his house in Cambridge the SNCC headquarters, Local people in Cambridge supported SNCC, Discussed how he got to McComb County Mississippi.
    - Reggie Robinson 2 June 6 2013.mp3, 0:07:12 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Short interview: Briefly discussed Bob Mants, Monroe Sharp, Guns and nonviolence.
  - Sellers, Cleve, 2013-08-01; 58
    - Cleve Sellers August 1 2013.mp3, 1:22:47 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Reaction to the name SNCC, students stuck out in his mind, Believed nonviolence was philosophical not tactical, He was in high school when he heard about SNCC from Ella Baker, Grew up with guns, self defense was understood to survive, white citizen's council became a more acceptable group. Philosophical non violence vs Tactical, most believed in Tactical. Discussed Meredith march.
  - Sherrod, Charles; Sherrod, Shirley, undated; 59
    - Sherrods.mp3, 0:56:24 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Transcript available. In person.
    - Transcript_Sherrods_CobbTNSGYK.docx (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
  - Stembridge, Jane, 2013-05-15; 60
    - Jane Stembridge 1 May 15 2013.mp3, 0:43:34 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. discussed SNCC beginnings, felt that the organization never would have become an SCLC youth group because most youth were skeptical of the adults, wanted their own voice. Discussed the meetings that led to the establishment of the permanent SNCC group. Discussed how she met Dr. King and was put into contact with Ella Baker, this was prior to the creation of SNCC. Discussed meeting Bob Moses and Bob's experiences in Mississippi. Discussed how the conversation of Voter Registration began.
    - Jane Stembridge 2 May 29 2013.mp3, 0:35:11 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Part 2. Continued conversation of Voter Registration. Discussed the differences between students from the cities and country side & north and south=they came in with different backgrounds but became one. Jane and Charlie discuss letters she wrote to Bob Moses. Jane wrote letters to introduce Bob Moses to local people including Amzie Moore.
  - Sullivan, Patricia, 2012-10-17; 61
    - Patricia Sullivan October 17 2012.mp3, 0:53:21 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview/bad quality: Discussing NAACP, DuBois, Johnson and White, Discusses the WWI period and WWII veterans
  - Swarez, Flukie, undated; 62
    - Flukie Swarez1.mp3, 0:04:08 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      A lot of background noise. Short interview Discussed C.O Chinn and Billy Noble, C.O Chinn and Billy Noble relationship, Noble respected C.O more than any other man.
    - Flukie Swarez2 main interview.mp3, 1:41:40 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Further discussion of C.O and feeling regret regarding how C.O was treated. Unique individual, provided much support to SNCC and the movement. Chinn lost everything (he had rental properties, nightclub and land) when SNCC left, but there was nobody who looked out after him. Movement people were too caught up in own priorities to help. Flukie left Mississippi and was torn up over Chaney killing.
  - Walker, Corey, 2013-05-01; 63
    - Corey Walker May 1 2013.mp3, 0:45:32 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Secret societies (prince hall masons), freemasonary, Concerns about masons, period. Gabriel's Rebellion, Nat Turner said to be a freemason.
  - Dennis, Dave, 2013-05-10; 64
    - Dave Dennis Part 1 May 10 2013_ Tougaloo College.mp3, 0:38:05 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Tougaloo College in Jackson, Mississippi. In person Interview Part 1. Talking about C.O Chinn, gun toting individual and he openly carried, Bill Noble of Canton,MS sherriff had mutual respect and disdain for one another. Discussion of blacks like Chinn that defied the status quo and being considered "crazy". Legacy of C.O Chinn, children became successful and the city honored him. (Canton,Madison County MS), C.O Chinn and family long time registered voters welcomed in SNCC because of the common goal of voter registration despite ideological differences. They weren't into the integration piece, more interested in political power. Discussion about CORE and policy on communities that refuse to disarm: we should not work with them, but Dave Dennis group believed they had no right to tell local people what to do. When New Orleans CORE people became involved with Deacons of Defense, there was a split became CORE South. Deacons became connected with Longshoreman union( powerful political group). Football, Jim Brown and actor Fred Williams: adopted Jonesboro group, supplied money and weapons. Chilly Willy organized Bogalusa group.
    - Dave Dennis Part 2 May 10 2013_ Tougaloo College.mp3, 0:02:26 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Tougaloo College in Jackson, Mississippi. In person Interview Part 2. Short clip discussing armed guys protecting churches in Shreveport and police would arrest them so bombing could commence and it was open war fare in that area.
  - Watkins, Hollis, 2012-07-18; 65
    - Hollis and Charlie discussion with teachers july 18 2012.mp3, 0:58:37 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Question and Answer session with teachers. Hollis discusses the moment he joined SNCC, formed Pike county non violent action committee attempted to integrate business there, Discussion of SNCC vision statement, said it was written by Nashville group and Jim Lewis, Attitude about nonviolence about a tactic, self defense is not the opposite of non violence, people compare being defensive with being violent. Students ask Hollis and Charlie about their relationships with white Mississippians. Explanation of "crazy negro" white people called black people who stand up for themselves that as a way to explaining why they leave them alone. Discrepancies between white Mississippians and later accounts of MS and what actually happened
    - hollis and cobb.mp3, 0:03:42 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
    - hollis at Fannie Lou Hamer Institute.mp3, 0:43:43 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      (Poor quality). Discussing experiences in McComb County MS, his movement beginnings: Got involved with NAACP in McComb before he got involved with SNCC, How freedom schools began: students involved in movement got expelled so it began as a way to educate them. Discusses work in Hattiesburg, MS as well, spent 55 days on death row and went into solitary confinement (The Hole). There is also a question and answer portion where Charlie Cobb and Hollis Watkins respond. Q and A's asked about women in the movement.
    - hollis fannie lou hamer institurte lecture.mp3, 0:43:43 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
    - Hollis Watkins June 4 2012.mp3, 0:48:07 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)